Pronnoy Dutta

+91 7042768041 | pronnoy1998@gmail.com LinkedIn | GitHub | Medium

Profile

Data Engineer with 4+ years of experience in building large-scale data pipelines, ETL processes, and data warehouse solutions. Utilized technologies like Python, SQL, Spark, AWS, ETL Pipelines, Hadoop and Kubernetes to develop multi-terabyte scalable big data solutions for Fortune 100 Pharmaceutical companies.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python, SQL, C#, Java

Big Data Technologies: Spark, PySpark, Spark SQL, YARN, Kubernetes, Hadoop, Hive Cloud Computing: AWS S3, AWS Glue, AWS EMR, AWS RDS, AWS Redshift Data Engineering Tools: Data Warehousing, Data Modelling, ETL/ELT data Pipeline

Orchestration: Airflow, Kubernetes, Control-M

Other Technologies: Tableau, Git, Linux, Microsoft Excel, Postman, MySQL, PostgresSQL, Docker

Certifications: AWS Certified Security Specialty, AWS Certified Solution Architect Associate, CCNA

EXPERIENCE

Axtria May 2024 - Present

Senior Data Engineer

Gurgaon, India

- Led a team of Data Engineers in designing, developing and optimizing data pipelines and ETL processes.
- Developed and optimized multiple complex SQL queries and ETL pipelines written in old technologies like Hive and SQL to more optimized big data technologies like PySpark, improving data processing efficiency by 30%.
- Carried out multiple change requests and SOW's in multiple projects at the same time using big data technologies like Airflow, Pyspark, AWS, Hadoop etc., handling various file formats like JSON, CSV and Parquet.
- Implemented Spark optimization techniques such as **caching**, **multithreading**, **and broadcast** joins, resulting in a 30% decrease in processing time for handling a daily load of around **5 Million records**.

Axtria Mar 2022 - April 2024

Associate Data Engineer/Analyst Data Engineer

Gurgaon, India

- Delivered multiple **development and scripting tasks** with zero defects, with proper DQ checks and email notifications wherever required, maintaining high-quality standards and client satisfaction.
- Independently developed and refined Tableau dashboards for cross-functional teams with real-time insights, facilitating data-driven decision-making. Automated the complete flow of refreshing around 30+ dashboards using a python script (tableau-api-lib package) and including the job resulting in 7 hours workforce decrease.
- Developed a microservice deployed on Kubernetes, integrating FastAPI to push messages into a **Kafka** broker for real-time tracking of processing status (success or failure).
- Developed multiple pipelines to ingest Business rules from backend using S3, developed dimension and fact data models and incorporated SCD-2 logic.
- Conducted in-depth data analysis using **Hive**, **Impala**, and **Spark SQL**, providing SIT/UAT fixes and ensuring smooth operations in the production environment.

Infosys November 2020 - March 2022

Systems Engineer

Remote

- Designed and implemented a Web API project using C# onion architecture, improving system performance by 15% and ensuring robust API functionality making use of tools like Swagger and Postman.
- Automated task scheduling and database operations using Python and SQL, reducing manual intervention by 50% and increasing operational efficiency.
- Created comprehensive CRUD APIs and unit tests, achieving a 95% code coverage and ensuring high-quality software delivery.

EDUCATION / OTHERS

• Bharati Vidyapeeth College of Engineering Pune

B.Tech Computer Science $\,$ July 2016 - June 2020 $\,$

• Delhi Public School, Gurgaon

Senior Secondary School 2016

• Official Member of AWS Community Builders – Member of Security Team